<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Toshiba Portege | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/toshiba-portege/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-07T15:11:47+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toshiba Portege Z830]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/12/toshiba-portege-z830.html"/>
    <updated>2011-12-10T07:21:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/12/toshiba-portege-z830</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you saw my <a href="/2011/11/13-core-i7-samsung-series-9-ultrabook.html">last post</a>, you would have seen that I recently bought a 13" Samsung Series 9 ultrabook &ndash; I still think these machines are stunning!</p>

<h2>The problem</h2>

<p>There are a couple of little complaints floating around about the Samsung, like heat output, easily finger-printed chasis, but none of these <em>really</em> bother me, but there is one thing that does&hellip; alot&hellip; and its the wifi!</p>

<p>I could be using the laptop in the next room from my wireless router and it would dropout completely or go incredibly slow, if I move to the other side of the house where my bedroom is, my phone will have full reception, but this laptop will not see the wifi network at all &ndash; and this in unacceptable.</p>

<h2>The transition</h2>

<p>After returning the laptop (twice) I eventually asked for my money back so I could go purchase my second preference &ndash; the Macbook Air.<br/>
Unfortunately, the shop would not give me a full refund and could only offer me a credit note.<br/>
I tried to explain that no other units in store could offer me the same specs that I was after, the Samsung&rsquo;s best competition is the Macbook Air, but as they couldn&rsquo;t help me I asked to see what else they have in a light 13".</p>

<p>The sales guy showed me an <a href="http://zenbook.asus.com/">Asus Zenbook</a> and a new product which had just arrived to their store, the <a href="http://us.toshiba.com/computers/laptops/portege/z830/">Toshiba Portege Z830</a>.<br/>
I was lucky enough to be the first to see this at their store and even got to open the display model and check it out.</p>

<p>The decision between the two was tough!<br/>
The Asus Zenbook had a very sturdy exterior and had a similar tapered  design to the Macbook Air while the Toshiba Portege had a business feel  to it, but was slightly lighter and thinner. <br/>
They were both similarly spec'ed with Core i5&rsquo;s, 128GB SSD&rsquo;s and 4GB of RAM, but there were a few notable differences between them.</p>

<p>Although the Asus Zenbook does not have a backlit keyboard and has reduced size ports, it does has a higher resolution screen than the Samsung and Toshiba, but like the Mac it&rsquo;s a glossy screen. I personally prefer matte screens because even in brightly lit areas or even outside in direct sunlight, the screen is alot more visible.</p>

<p>The Toshiba Portege has a matte screen, backlit keyboard, has a full size HDMI port, VGA port, Ethernet port, 2x USB 2.0 ports, 1x USB 3.0 port and SD card reader and its thinner and lighter. Toshiba also give a 3 year warranty out-of-the-box with this model.<br/>
The screen is quite a bit more flimsy than the others and the system fan does tend to groan a little (compared to the Samsung at least), but this is probably all I can complain about.</p>

<h2>The solution</h2>

<p>I took a day to think about it and eventually made up my mind for the Portege.<br/>
In the US, there is an i7 variety with 6GB of RAM, but I don&rsquo;t really want to wait for it to get here.<br/>
I took a look at a <a href="http://ark.intel.com/compare/54616,56858">comparison</a> between the i7 from the Samsung and the i5 from the Toshiba, and while I would have paid the extra for the i7, I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll really notice the difference in most scenarios.</p>

<p>It seems I am not the only one who ended up swapping a Samsung Series 9 for a Toshiba Portege Z830 either, I came across this <a href="http://thessdreview.com/our-reviews/sata-3/toshiba-z830-13-3-ultrabook-laptop-review-toshiba-creates-one-amazing-ultrabook/">blog post</a> where the author goes into more detail and provides results of quite specific tests.</p>

<p>In the end I paid $1539 for the laptop with a 3 year warranty and then an extra $79 to upgrade it to 6GB of RAM.<br/>
While it&rsquo;s no Samsung Series 9, its pretty nice and the cut in performance saved me a little more than $600.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
