<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: review | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-07T21:56:52+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Samsung Galaxy S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/2012/08/samsung-galaxy-s3.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-21T12:50:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/2012/08/samsung-galaxy-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
At the end of June this year, I upgraded from a HTC Desire HD to a Samsung Galaxy S3, so I thought after a couple of months of having my new phone I should write up a (really long) post on what stood out for me.<br /><br /><br /><b>The positive</b> <br /><br />The <b>screen and form factor</b> is awesome! Due to the plastic body and the thin shape, this phone is really light and slips into your pocket nicely. The massive 4.8" screen really shines when watching videos and browsing the web. I regularly watch screencasts on my phone and the 1280x720 resolution gives me plenty of detail. The colour contrast is a lot higher than my previous phone, which makes the blacks look really deep and videos stand out nicely. The marketing video that the phone comes with does demo it off quite well!<br /><br />The <b>battery </b>is fairly good. My requirement for battery life is that I can use it all day and by the time I get home / go to bed, it hasn't died. Not a high expectation, I know, but these days its hard to expect more. This phone meets that requirement quite easily. On the days I don't use my phone much, I get home after a days work with more than 50% remaining (which is huge compared to my last phone!) and on the days I use it quite heavily, I get home to about 30%-40% which easily lasts me the rest of the night. My usage generally includes syncing gmail, facebook, twitter, weather, RSS reader, work email (during peak hours), I am generally connected to wifi most of the time and I regularly browse the web and watch videos / listen to podcasts during my commute.<br /><br />The general<b> responsiveness</b> is miles ahead of my last phone too! Day-to-day usage is smooth and rarely experience any lag. This will be improved even more when Jellybean is released (rumoured to be soon!).<br /><br /><b>"Smart Stay" </b>is a new innovative feature from Samsung where just before the screen is about to timeout and turn off, the phone will take a photo of you with the front-facing camera and use face (or eye) detection to work out if you're still looking at it. If you are, it will keep it on for another minute or so, if you're not, then it will dim the screen and check again soon after, which then will actually turn it off.<br />This is to avoid that randomly-scrolling-to-avoid-the-screen-turning-off trick that most people will do when reading a long article. Thankfully, this feature is quite effective and I haven't needed to do that for a while, although it doesn't work very well in the dark!<br /><br />In the settings, there is a section called <b>"Motion"</b>. I won't go through all of the options, as there are about 10 different ones, but some are quite handy. By far the best one IMHO is <b>"Direct call"</b>, which lets you directly call a contact whose call log details, contact details or message details are displayed on the screen by simply putting the phone to your ear from that screen. Feels very natural.<br />Another nice one is <b>"Smart alert"</b>, which will give a little vibration when you pick it up from a stationary location if you have a missed call or sms.<br /><br />The <b>camera</b> on this phone is not too bad either. Obviously it will never replace my dSLR, but it has some nice features that even my dSLR doesn't have. The burst fire mode is really quick, but Samsung have introduced a feature called <b>"best shot"</b>, which will analyse each of the photos you took in the burst and pick the ones it thinks turned out the best, based on focus and face detection. You can adjust what was picked, and then the others are automatically discarded (saves you having to go through the 14 bad ones and delete them later).<br />The camera has a <b>built-in HDR</b> mode which works quite well too and the <b>photo editor</b> provides heaps of enhancements and corrections, including red-eye reduction, color balance, cropping, etc.<br /><br />Another nice feature is found in the video player, it has a <b>"pop-out"</b> button! This means that if you're in the middle of a video and you wanted to quickly google something, or reply to an sms, you can just pop out the video, which turns the full screen player into a small, floating, always on top window that you can drag around, do what you need to do, and then make it full screen again. Not something that I've needed to use very often, but on the rare occasion I have, it's been quite nice.<br /><br />I use my calendar religiously and on my older HTC, the default app looked nice, but didn't have many features. I ended up swapping it out for <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=netgenius.bizcal&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">Business Calendar Free</a> just so I could get a month view with text, instead of indicators.<br />The stock Samsung calendar, <b>S Planner</b>, however is not too bad! It integrates with their S Memo, which I don't use, but comes with a good number of viewing options, my favourites being their month view and analogue week view. It also has a nice <b>"Quick add" </b>feature that lets you enter "Dinner at Nandos tomorrow 7:30pm" and it does what you'd expect. This doesn't support anywhere near as much as Google Calendar does, but its better than nothing!<br /><br />I lashed out and bought an <b>official Samsung Desktop Dock</b>, and comparing this to my cheap eBay special I bought for my HTC, not only does it look quite nice, but it automatically launches the desktop clock app when I dock it and after 5 minutes it dims the screen and hides the other UI elements other than the clock. I like this feature a lot because I otherwise don't have a clock in my room, so its really handy for me!<br /><br /><br />As with all things, there are pro's and con's. Here are some of the things I don't like. <br /><br /><br /><b>The negative</b><br /><br />Android have decided to <b>remove USB Mass Storage mode</b> (my biggest pet hate with Android right now!) This leaves you with 3 alternative options for copying files to and from the device: Media Transfer Protocol (MTP), Camera mode or using an app such as <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.samsung.swift.app.kiesair&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">Kies Air</a> or <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=xcxin.filexpert&amp;feature=search_result#?t=W251bGwsMSwxLDEsInhjeGluLmZpbGV4cGVydCJd" target="_blank">File Expert</a>.<br />MTP and Camera mode both don't give you access to all the directories on the phone, but for just transferring media it should be ok. Note that MTP will work out of the box with Windows, but if you run Mac or Linux like me, you will need to install software to get it to work (and Linux is a pain for this!).<br />The reason for this change is because USB Mass Storage mode will mean you have to unmount the partition from the system in order to mount it to the computer, whereas MTP will allow you to access it in both places at once, but its slower and requires software.<br />For phones like the Galaxy Nexus, this makes sense as there is only one partition, but with the S3, I would like to see the option of just unmounting the memory card (with is separate from the system storage) and allow that to work with USB Mass Storage mode.<br /><br />Another annoying thing I have found with this phone is sometimes the <b>home screen will randomly die</b>. This causes lag while all the widgets reinitialise themselves. It doesn't happen often, but when it does, its annoying considering its a simple software issue. Hopefully this is fixed with Jellybean release!<br /><br />On a related note, I find the random delay between pressing the <b>unlock button</b> and the screen actually turning on to be annoying too, considering my older HTC was basically instantaneous everytime, this phone seems to vary quite a lot. I find myself pressing the button while its still in my pocket, just so by the time I have it in front of me, the screen is ready.<br /><br />A couple of other minor things include the <b>notification LED</b> being really bright, which is ok, but while the phone is docked my bedside, it will light up the entire room quite easily. This is kind of funny considering "smart stay" doesn't work well at night. Maybe instead of just green and red, the LED should have also included an IR LED for that.<br />Not only is the LED really bright, but when the battery becomes fully charged, it will turn on the screen and popup a notification, which is also not very nice when I'm trying to sleep.<br />I know most of you are probably thinking a solution would be to turn it off at night, but I <a href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/xkcd-beyondpod.html" target="_blank">scheduled my phone to download podcasts</a> during these hours with <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=mobi.beyondpod&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">BeyondPod</a> - I think the pro's outweigh the con's in this situation.<br /><br />Also minor, but there is <b>no stock flashlight app</b>, which I wanted to put in the lock screen shortcuts. It does come with a 2x1 widget, but to get a shortcut on the lock screen, I ended up downloading one of the million flashlight apps out there.<br /><br />Speaking of widgets, the HTC widgets were really nice, but I find the <b>widgets</b> that came with the Samsung are not quite as useful, luckily they are in abundance on the play store too!<br /><br /><br /><b>The other stuff</b><br /><br />Here are some other noteworthy things which I haven't really made up my mind if I like yet or not.<br /><br />The music player has a feature called <b>"Music Square"</b> and I love the idea of it, but I'm not sure how effective it is. Basically you index your music library and it categorises each of your songs into 2 scales: <i>'Exciting</i> to <i>Calm'</i> and <i>'Passionate</i> to <i>Joyful</i>'. These two scales make up the axes of the music square and by tapping where your mood is will play those types of songs. It's a great idea and I need to experiment with it more to see how effective it is.<br /><br />A lot of the features in the phone are <b>voice activated</b>. For example, you can say <i>'answer'</i> or <i>'reject'</i> when it is ringing (as long as the ringtone isn't too loud); <i>'snooze'</i> or <i>'stop'</i> when the alarm is going off (as long as thats not too loud); <i>'smile'</i>, <i>'cheese'</i>, <i>'capture'</i> or <i>'shoot'</i> to take a photo (as long as your close enough for the phone to hear you); <i>'next'</i>, <i>'previous'</i>, <i>'pause'</i>, <i>'play'</i>, <i>'volume'</i>, etc. to control your music or the radio (as long as thats not too loud either).<br />As you can see, the usefulness of these features are dependant on the environment.<br /><br /><b>S Voice</b> is Samsung's answer to Siri, and even the UI's look similar, but while its great in theory, I think the most useful thing about Siri on the iPhone or S Voice on the Galaxy would be SMS/email dictation, but that is the one thing these features don't work that well for, at least for me anyway - maybe its just my voice!<br /><br /><br /><b>The conclusion</b><br /><br />In the end I am very happy with my new phone, it is leaps and bounds above my old phone, its really responsive other than the random home screen lag and unlock button delay, it has some nice new innovative features and is a joy to use.<br />Also, with the Jellybean release (hopefully) around the corner, it can only get better.
</div>


<div class="css-full-comments-content js-full-comments-content">
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/06966628689154715916">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    optiks
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-08-22T03:09:53.174Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Jeez, that was so thorough you could be a horse :)
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/17635851344281945521">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Steven Occhipinti
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-08-22T03:13:44.550Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Haha! Yea, had a list of dot points that accumulated a bit, then when I wrote a &quot;quick&quot; paragraph on each one, it kind of exploded :P<br />Not expecting many people to read it all, unless they are considering buying one and they happen to be like me :P then its all about the details!
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/13228213079214942610">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Todd Growcott
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-08-24T22:34:28.376Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Totaly agree with your review...just wondering if u had an issue with songs randomly skipping and restarting half way through.If so help would be greatly appreciated..cheers:)
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/17635851344281945521">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Steven Occhipinti
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-08-25T13:08:18.822Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Thanks for the feedback Todd.<br />I&#39;m sorry but I can&#39;t say I&#39;ve had that issue before.<br />A friend of mine had a similar issue with a HTC phone, the problem turned out to be with the headphone jack.<br />Basically when he wiggled the headphone plug it would skip and pause, etc. because of the way corded remote controls works.<br />This also meant that when he wasn&#39;t playing music, sometimes the headphones would cause the phone to redial the last number.<br />I&#39;d suggest contacting the retailer or customer care and showing them the problem, they may be able to replace it for you.<br />Good luck!
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toshiba Portege Z830]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/2011/12/toshiba-portege-z830.html"/>
    <updated>2011-12-10T07:21:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/2011/12/toshiba-portege-z830</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
If you saw my <a href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/11/13-core-i7-samsung-series-9-ultrabook.html">last post</a>, you would have seen that I recently bought a 13" Samsung Series 9 ultrabook - I still think these machines are stunning!<br /><br /><br /><b>The problem</b><br /><br />There are a couple of little complaints floating around about the Samsung, like heat output, easily finger-printed chasis, but none of these <i>really</i> bother me, but there is one thing that does... alot... and its the wifi!<br /><br />I could be using the laptop in the next room from my wireless router and it would dropout completely or go incredibly slow, if I move to the other side of the house where my bedroom is, my phone will have full reception, but this laptop will not see the wifi network at all - and this in unacceptable.<br /><br /><br /><b>The transition</b><br /><br />After returning the laptop (twice) I eventually asked for my money back so I could go purchase my second preference - the Macbook Air.<br />Unfortunately, the shop would not give me a full refund and could only offer me a credit note.<br />I tried to explain that no other units in store could offer me the same specs that I was after, the Samsung's best competition is the Macbook Air, but as they couldn't help me I asked to see what else they have in a light 13".<br /><br />The sales guy showed me an <a href="http://zenbook.asus.com/" target="_blank">Asus Zenbook</a> and a new product which had just arrived to their store, the <a href="http://us.toshiba.com/computers/laptops/portege/z830/" target="_blank">Toshiba Portege Z830</a>.<br />I was lucky enough to be the first to see this at their store and even got to open the display model and check it out.<br /><br />The decision between the two was tough!<br />The Asus Zenbook had a very sturdy exterior and had a similar tapered  design to the Macbook Air while the Toshiba Portege had a business feel  to it, but was slightly lighter and thinner. <br />They were both similarly spec'ed with Core i5's, 128GB SSD's and 4GB of RAM, but there were a few notable differences between them.<br /><br />Although the Asus Zenbook does not have a backlit keyboard and has reduced size ports, it does has a higher resolution screen than the Samsung and Toshiba, but like the Mac it's a glossy screen. I personally prefer matte screens because even in brightly lit areas or even outside in direct sunlight, the screen is alot more visible. <br /><br />The Toshiba Portege has a matte screen, backlit keyboard, has a full size HDMI port, VGA port, Ethernet port, 2x USB 2.0 ports, 1x USB 3.0 port and SD card reader and its thinner and lighter. Toshiba also give a 3 year warranty out-of-the-box with this model.<br />The screen is quite a bit more flimsy than the others and the system fan does tend to groan a little (compared to the Samsung at least), but this is probably all I can complain about.<br /><br /><br /><b>The solution</b><br /><br />I took a day to think about it and eventually made up my mind for the Portege.<br />In the US, there is an i7 variety with 6GB of RAM, but I don't really want to wait for it to get here.<br />I took a look at a <a href="http://ark.intel.com/compare/54616,56858" target="_blank">comparison</a> between the i7 from the Samsung and the i5 from the Toshiba, and while I would have paid the extra for the i7, I don't think I'll really notice the difference in most scenarios.<br /><br />It seems I am not the only one who ended up swapping a Samsung Series 9 for a Toshiba Portege Z830 either, I came across this <a href="http://thessdreview.com/our-reviews/sata-3/toshiba-z830-13-3-ultrabook-laptop-review-toshiba-creates-one-amazing-ultrabook/" target="_blank">blog post</a> where the author goes into more detail and provides results of quite specific tests.<br /><br />In the end I paid $1539 for the laptop with a 3 year warranty and then an extra $79 to upgrade it to 6GB of RAM.<br />While it's no Samsung Series 9, its pretty nice and the cut in performance saved me a little more than $600.
</div>


<div class="css-full-comments-content js-full-comments-content">
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="undefined">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Anonymous
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2011-12-12T05:03:18.481Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Nice post Steve...<br /><br />If you dig a little deeper you will notice that I was the only reviewer to identify the severe Series 9 wifi problems initially, problems which are still prevalent today:<br /><br />http://thessdreview.com/our-reviews/the-samsung-series-9-13-900x3a-a01ca-review-this-may-be-a-work-of-art-almost/
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/17635851344281945521">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Steven Occhipinti
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2011-12-12T10:29:44.702Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Thanks! I appreciate the feedback :)<br /><br />I did read that post too and while it did scare me, I immediately asked a friend (who also owns one) if he had experienced the same issues, which he didn&#39;t - so with mixed feedback and such a nice machine, I just had to try.<br /><br />After some issues, I ended up doing the same wifi speed comparisons as you with other laptops in the house and got mixed results - which unfortunately I could not prove to the store at the time I returned it.<br /><br />Needless to say, like yourself, I am very disappointed as I started to become attached to the very well built machine.<br /><br />It&#39;s a real shame, but the Toshiba is going strong so far :)
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/16990772765126563718">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Les Tokar
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2011-12-21T03:20:09.123Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Nice call Steven and thats coming from the site owner at &#39;that blogpost&#39; eheheh.  I went through 4 x Series 9 laptops before getting the Z830, mine being an i7.  IMHO, the lid isn&#39;t flimsy, but rather, reflective of just how thin it is. It is the thinnest ultra on the market.<br /><br />I as well have read all the comments regarding fan issues but have yet to be bothered by mine whatsoever.  I expected such with a laptop that is this thin in any case.<br /><br />Again nice post!
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/17635851344281945521">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Steven Occhipinti
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2011-12-21T03:56:55.782Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Haha, thanks Les :) Means a lot to me!<br /><br />Wow, you went through 4! I went through 2 and the shop were getting quite annoyed with me, lol.<br /><br />After using the screen for a while now, I do actually like the thickness of it, and the fan noise is only evident when there is no other background noise around (like late at night).<br /><br />My complaints with the Toshiba are very minor, but I am very happy with this machine.<br /><br />As I run 2 operating systems, one day I&#39;ll have to consider upgrading the SSD and I&#39;m sure your site will be of great help to me when that time comes!<br /><br />Thanks for the comments :)
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="undefined">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Judd
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-02-21T03:38:50.976Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    I know it&#39;s too late for you now (congrats on the Toshiba, looks like a nice machine!) but I recently saw this on the Samsung Q&amp;A website, and thought it might help other people Googling for this issue.  I haven&#39;t confirmed that it works, but another commenter on the Q&amp;A site did.<br /><br />From: http://www.samsung.com/us/support/allQuestion.do?prd_mdl_name=NP900X3A<br /><br /><br />A : I can&#39;t speak for the Broadcom WiFi card, but for the Intel card (and perhaps also for the Broadcom card), the issue is with the default power management settings. If the laptop works well when plugged in and using the &quot;Samsung Optimized&quot; power plan but works poorly when not plugged in, this is your issue. To fix it, go to Control Panel (View by: Small icons) *or* right click on the battery icon in the system tray area, then select Power Options. For the current plan, click Change plan settings, then click Change advanced power settings. Expand Wireless Adapter Settings, expand Power Saving Mode, then set Plugged in: to &quot;Maximum Performance&quot; (see screenshot). This is the only setting that works properly--I&#39;ve tried all of them. Make this change for all of the power plans, or at least all of the ones you intend to use.
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/06780719137908868809">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Mike Lewis
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-03-16T14:46:15.289Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    How do you feel about the performance with Ubuntu? I just bought a Portege Z830 fully-loaded and it seems to lock up at least a couple of times a day on heavy IO tasks. That may be just because I&#39;m running a Wubi install though (couldn&#39;t wait to get Ubuntu installed).
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
<div class="css-full-comment js-full-comment">
  <div class="css-comment-user-link js-comment-user-link">
  <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/17635851344281945521">
  <div class="css-comment-name js-comment-name">
    Steven Occhipinti
  </div>
  </a>
  <div class="css-comment-date js-comment-date">
    2012-03-18T04:56:59.253Z
  </div>
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-title js-comment-title">
    Hi Mike,

I have had a great experience with Ubunt...
  </div>
  <div class="css-comment-content js-comment-content">
    Hi Mike,<br /><br />I have had a great experience with Ubuntu.<br />I&#39;m running Ubuntu 11.10 with Gnome Shell and have never really seen any lag or lockups.<br />I haven&#39;t made any optimizations or anything, its all just stock standard.<br /><br />I haven&#39;t tried Wubi on this machine, I have partitioned my 128GB SSD down the middle, which doesn&#39;t leave alot of space per OS.<br />I am even considering taking Windows off, considering I barely ever use it these days.
  </div>
  <br/>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[13" Core i7 Samsung Series 9 Ultrabook]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/2011/11/13-core-i7-samsung-series-9-ultrabook.html"/>
    <updated>2011-11-28T00:34:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenocchipinti.github.io/2011/11/13-core-i7-samsung-series-9-ultrabook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
Back in my first year of uni, I bought one of the early Core Duo (not Core 2 Duo) 15" Asus laptops which at the time was great and it had a decent graphics card for games, etc.<br />Roughly 6 years later, its showing its age. The battery lasts less than an hour now, it weighs about 3kg not including the adapter and performance is lacking compared to todays technology.<br /><br />After a recent shoulder injury and a busy week that involved me carrying my laptop from place to place, I decided it was time to reward myself with an early Christmas present and buy a new machine.<br /><br />My requirements were:<br /><ul><li>13" screen</li><li>As thin and as light as possible to aid portability</li><li>Powerful enough to do almost anything my daily activities could involve</li><li>&lt;~ $2000 </li></ul>I compared as many of these 13" <i>"ultrabooks"</i> as I could and before long I had created a shortlist of my top 3 - which included an Asus u-Series, a Macbook Air and a Samsung Series 9.<br /><br /><br /><b>Asus u-Series</b><br /><br />The <a href="http://www.asus.com.au/Notebooks/Superior_Mobility/U36SD/#specifications" target="_blank">Asus machines</a>, as usual, had a very good bang-for-buck, a nice thickness of 19mm and unlike most others, some models had full size video output and ethernet plugs.<br />While the price and size were right, the highest spec'ed machines were not quite as impressive as its competition. If budget was the number one concern, the Asus u-Series and Zenbook range offer pretty good value.<br /><br /><br /><b>Macbook Air</b><br /><br />I have never been a <i>"Mac person"</i> due to the traditional heavy pricing and proprietary nature of alot of their products, but these days (after some convincing) I believe the hardware and even price does have a surprisingly strong position in the competition.<br />The <a href="http://store.apple.com/au/browse/home/shop_mac/family/macbook_pro" target="_blank">13" Macbook Pro</a> and <a href="http://www.apple.com/au/macbookair/specs.html" target="_blank">Macbook Air</a> both had very good specs to offer for around the $2000 price tag, both with Core i7's, 4-8GB RAM and SSD's, not to mention pretty attractive packaging.<br />After seeing a Macbook Air up close, I really liked how the thickest point is about 17mm or so at the back but it tapers off to next to nothing at the front.<br /><br />So the model I chose for comparison purposes was worth $1928.99 and had the following specs:<br /><ul><li>1.8GHz Dual-Core Intel Core i7</li><li>4GB 1333MHz DDR3 SDRAM</li><li>256GB flash storage</li><li>Mini DisplayPort to DVI adapter ($30)</li></ul>I don't like the very proprietary DisplayPort and its $30 adapters, but its not too bad as almost <i>everyone </i>at my office uses a Mac so finding a spare adapter when needed wouldn't be too hard (I guess popularity offsets proprietary-ness).<br /><br />The operating system did not bother me too much either as I intended to be running Linux as my primary OS anyway, but having a Mac would give me more familiarity with OSX which would be helpful considering its popularity in my line of work.<br /><br />The minor annoyances would be: expensive adapters for video and ethernet ports, unfamiliar keyboard layout (command key where alt should be, etc), non-upgradeable ram, glossy screen, etc. - but those are pretty minor.<br /><br /><br /><b>Samsung Series 9</b><br /><br />I found these ultrabooks to have a very unique look and one of the first well thought out, thin designs that are not just another Mac look-a-like.<br />The sales pitch always includes a spiel about its "Duralumin"- which is a light and strong material used in aircrafts and while it looks stunning and adds sophistication and uniqueness to the overall design on the unit, this material along with the black plastic are both fingerprint magnets!<br /><br />The <a href="http://www.samsung.com/au/consumer/pc-peripherals/notebook-pc/thin-light/NP900X3A-A03AU/index.idx?pagetype=prd_detail&amp;tab=specification" target="_blank">specs of the Series 9 unit</a> I used for comparison (and ultimately bought) was quite good:<br /><ul><li>1.5GHz Core i7</li><li>8GB RAM</li><li>256GB SSD</li><li>Micro-HDMI to HDMI adapter ($15) </li></ul>Initially I thought 1.5 GHz was kinda low, but after conversations with quite a few people and some <a href="http://ark.intel.com/compare/54616" target="_blank">research</a>, this speed is its sort-of <i>"resting"</i> frequency and will automatically scale up to 2.6GHz when required.<br /><br />The one big catch with this system is the RRP of ~$2700, while most Aussie shops sold them for ~$2500. This made me consider the Mac even more!<br /><br />But during my research I saw <a href="https://www.mln.com.au/" target="_blank">MLN</a>'s price drop down to a much more attractive $1997 and immediately rang them to find out more details and how long the special would last. It turns out that Samsung are starting to phase them out of stores (presumably to make way for a new product next year) and naturally they had sold alot of units and only had a few left.<br /><br />I did a bit more research and found that to save space, the ports are hidden behind very aircraft-like flaps, but as with the Mac, they are reduced size ports.<br />The video output is provided in the form of a micro-HDMI port - which is at least a more common format and I don't need to go through apple.com.<br />The other space-saving trade-off was a (sadly) proprietary ethernet port that comes bundled with an adapter to convert it to RJ45 - but unlike the Mac where you need to buy a USB network adapter, this actually has the network card built in, it just has an unusual plug - which I don't intend to use much anyway.<br /><br />Another plus is this model comes with 1x USB 3.0 port (and a 2.0 port) which is great considering the speeds my brother gets with his USB 3.0 flash drive.<br /><br />So I went to MLN and inspected the unit up close and what eventually made my decision for the Samsung was that for about the same price I get a machine with double the RAM (handy for VMs), a windows licence for portable gaming and a bunch of freebies from MLN including the HDMI to micro-HDMI cable, a set of Sennheiser headphones and a padded sleeve to carry it.<br /><br />I was able to get the cable and sleeve free because I opted to purchase the extended 3 year pickup warranty for an additional $180ish and the headphones were a Christmas present :)<br /><br />Initial impressions are very positive, the screen is incredibly bright and vibrant and with a smooth matte finish, I have had no issues using it outdoors.<br />The backlit keyboard is quite nice too, although the brightness of this light is controlled via windows drivers, so in linux (at this stage) I cant control its brightness.<br />The touchpad is large and seems to employ the same technique as the Mac Magic Mouse where there is one click-able button (the lower part of the pad) and depending on where your finger is when you click determines a right or left mouse click and once again, this doesnt work in Linux out of the box, but the standard 2 finger tap works as per normal.<br />Using Ubuntu 11.10 the rest of the hardware works out of the box, so no need to fiddle with drivers for network, graphics, webcam, etc.<br /><br />Overall I am very happy with my purchase and its a huge step up from my old 15.4" 3kg laptop!
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
