<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: minecraft | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/minecraft/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-30T22:43:51+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing Minecraft in Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2013/11/10/installing-minecraft-in-linux/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-10T12:26:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2013/11/10/installing-minecraft-in-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>1. Download Oracle Java</h2>

<p>First you will need the official Oracle version of Java (the open source
alternatives will probably not work as well for Minecraft). I think you can
just download the runtime, but I personally opt for installing the complete
Java Development Kit (JDK).</p>

<p>You can download the <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/jdk7-downloads-1880260.html">official JDK here</a>.<br/>
If you run a RedHat based distro, there is a <code>.rpm</code>, otherwise just get the
<code>.tgz</code> for your system.</p>

<h2>2. Installing Oracle Java</h2>

<p>At the time of writing, the version of java is 7u45.<br/>
I move this <code>.tar.gz</code> file from my downloads folder to <code>/opt</code> and unzip it
there, like this:
<code>
mv ~/Downloads/jdk-7u45-linux-x64.tar.gz /opt
cd /opt
tar xzvf jdk-7u45-linux-x64.tar.gz
</code></p>

<p>This will create a new directory called <code>jdk1.7.0_45</code>.<br/>
As there is a good chance we will be updating java in the future, I create a
symlink that we can easily change to the new versions in the future like this:
<code>
ln -s jdk1.7.0_45 jdk
</code></p>

<p>Now when ever you want to find java, it will be in <code>/opt/jdk</code>.</p>

<p>All we have to do now is make the executables available on the <code>PATH</code>.<br/>
Edit your <code>.bashrc</code> (or <code>.profile</code>, etc.) and add this line:
<code>
export PATH=$PATH:/opt/jdk/bin/
</code></p>

<h2>3. Install Minecraft</h2>

<p>Get Minecraft from the <a href="https://minecraft.net/download">official Minecraft download page</a>.
Under the &ldquo;Minecraft for Linux / Other&rdquo; there is a link to download the
official Minecraft <code>.jar</code> file.  I also put this in <code>/opt</code>:
<code>
mkdir /opt/minecraft
mv ~/Downloads/Minecraft.jar /opt/minecraft
</code></p>

<p>At this point we can start Minecraft with this:
<code>
java -jar Minecraft.jar
</code></p>

<h2>4. Setting up an Application Launcher for Gnome</h2>

<p>I use Gnome Shell and if I&rsquo;m not in a terminal, I normally use Gnome&rsquo;s
<em>Activities Overview</em> to launch apps by pressing the &lsquo;super&rsquo; key, typing
&ldquo;Minecraft&rdquo; and pressing &lsquo;enter&rsquo;.</p>

<p>We want Minecraft to be installed just like any other app, so we will need to
add a launcher for Minecraft, but before we do that, we need an icon for it.
I just found one online, so lets download it to our <code>/opt/minecraft</code> directory.</p>

<p><code>
cd /opt/minecraft
wget http://images.wikia.com/yogbox/images/d/dd/Minecraft_Block.svg
</code></p>

<p>Then to make an application launcher, you can use this:
<code>
gnome-desktop-item-edit --create-new ~/.local/share/applications
</code></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-9VnJ9K_nqQo/Un72Np6LzPI/AAAAAAAABTg/PVig82azah8/w435-h224-no">https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-9VnJ9K_nqQo/Un72Np6LzPI/AAAAAAAABTg/PVig82azah8/w435-h224-no</a>"></p>

<p>You can assign it the logo we downloaded earlier and use this for the command:
<code>
/opt/jdk/bin/java -jar /opt/minecraft/Minecraft.jar
</code></p>

<h2>5. Have fun!</h2>

<p>Now you can launch Minecraft just like the other apps in Gnome Shell!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minecraft exception in linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/02/minecraft-exception-in-linux.html"/>
    <updated>2012-02-02T12:25:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/02/minecraft-exception-in-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally decided to install Minecraft on my new shiny <a href="/2011/12/toshiba-portege-z830.html">Toshiba Portege z830</a>.<br/>
Ubuntu ships with an open-source version of Java, which did run Minecraft, but the graphics were terrible, even on the lowest settings. There were artefacts everywhere!</p>

<p>So as recommended, I switched to the official JRE. Now the login screen works, but that&rsquo;s about it. After logging in, I just got a black screen and the following exception in the console:</p>

<p><code>
Exception in thread "Minecraft main thread"
java.lang.ExceptionInInitializerError at
net.minecraft.client.Minecraft.a(SourceFile:180) at
net.minecraft.client.Minecraft.run(SourceFile:648) at
java.lang.Thread.run(Thread.java:662)&lt;div class="de2"&gt;Caused by: java.lang.ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException: 0 at
org.lwjgl.opengl.XRandR$Screen.&amp;lt;init&amp;gt;(XRandR.java:234) at
org.lwjgl.opengl.XRandR$Screen.&amp;lt;init&amp;gt;(XRandR.java:196) at
org.lwjgl.opengl.XRandR.populate(XRandR.java:87) at
org.lwjgl.opengl.XRandR.access$100(XRandR.java:52)at
org.lwjgl.opengl.XRandR$1.run(XRandR.java:110) at
java.security.AccessController.doPrivileged(Native Method) at
org.lwjgl.opengl.XRandR.getConfiguration(XRandR.java:108) at
org.lwjgl.opengl.LinuxDisplay.init(LinuxDisplay.java:618) at
org.lwjgl.opengl.Display.&amp;lt;clinit&amp;gt;(Display.java:135)
... 3 more
</code></p>

<p>After discussing the problem in IRC, the solution was quite simple. It turns out <code>lwjgl</code> is a &ldquo;<em>Light Weight Java Game Library</em>&rdquo; and the version I had wasn&rsquo;t behaving.<br/>
On the advice of the helpful IRC'ers, I downloaded the latest <code>lwjgl</code> from <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/java-game-lib/files/Official%20Releases/">here</a> (which at time of writing is 2.8.3) to get it all to work nicely.</p>

<p>To install it, I downloaded the zip file, extracted it to a temporary directory, then copied across these files:</p>

<p><code>
cp lwjgl-2.8.3/jar/lwjgl.jar ~/.minecraft/bin
cp lwjgl-2.8.3/native/linux/* ~/.minecraft/bin/natives
</code></p>

<p>Done! Now it works nicely.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[(Minecraft and) Arch Linux FTW!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/04/minecraft-and-arch-linux-ftw.html"/>
    <updated>2011-04-16T08:25:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/04/minecraft-and-arch-linux-ftw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
I haven't really played a game properly since back in my Counter Strike days, but recently my brother and I started playing <a href="http://www.minecraft.net/">Minecraft</a>... and its incredibly addictive!<br /><br />Minecraft give you the option of running a Java based dedicated server and so as we were starting out, my brother would start up a dedicated server and we would both connect to it.<br />As time went on, we thought it would be really cool to have a dedicated Minecraft box and thought we could build one out of some old hardware, which brings me to the HTPC!<br /><br />A little while ago, my brother built this (the black box):<br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-7dL37EFmdbw/TalNVGQgTII/AAAAAAAAAuU/9mIJYfk8Z48/s1600/IMAG0146.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="191" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-7dL37EFmdbw/TalNVGQgTII/AAAAAAAAAuU/9mIJYfk8Z48/s320/IMAG0146.jpg" width="320" /></a></div><br /><br />He did an awesome job!<br />Basically gutted our very first dvd player (which was great for its time) and got some cheap (physically small) hardware off eBay and managed to fit it all inside! <br />It involved making alot of little brackets, extender cables, etc. but with a lot of effort it turned out pretty impressive!<br /><br />Unfortunately, using it as a media pc was a bit tough as it wasn't the most powerful of machines around and the graphics drivers weren't working too well so this got left in the dust for a while... until Minecraft came along!<br /><br />Last weekend we decided to make this our dedicated server :)<br />A while ago a friend of a friend was talking about how good Arch Linux was for its simplicity and ease of administration, so I started reading up on it and I am impressed!<br /><br />On the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/">Arch Linux wiki</a> they have a couple of <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Beginners%27_Guide">guides</a> to help you get going, but my favorite page was the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Boot">explanation of the boot process</a>.<br />After a bit of reading I worked out my plan of attack:<br /><ul><li>Burn ISO to cd</li><li>Install Arch Linux</li><li>Install sudo (via pacman)&nbsp;</li><li>Setup 'minecraft' user with sudo access to the poweroff command</li><li>Install Java (via pacman)</li><li>Install rungetty (via AUR)</li><li>Replace 'agetty' with 'rungetty' and make the minecraft server startup on tty1, followed by a 'poweroff'</li><li>Configure Wake-On-Lan</li></ul><br />After the server was all setup, I wrote a little client side wrapper that will:<br /><ul><li>Launch minecraft</li><li>Broadcast a magic-packet to power on the server</li><li>Start pinging it and when it is available, notify me via Ubuntu's 'notify-send' command</li></ul><br />So now when I want to play Minecraft, I launch my script and it will power on the server and launch the client, I log in, wait about 5 seconds until my fancy fade-in notification appears, then join the server, play, and when im done, I issue the '/stop' command in Minecraft and it will stop the server and power it self off!<br /><br />This was a great first experiment with Arch Linux and I didn't even know what getty was before this day.<br /><br />Needless to say I was pretty happy with this setup and all in a days work :)
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
