<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: xbmc | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/xbmc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-14T23:27:35+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[XBMC Eden + Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/04/xbmc-eden-ubuntu.html"/>
    <updated>2012-04-06T10:23:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/04/xbmc-eden-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back when I started uni, I bought a new <a href="http://www.notebookreview.com/default.asp?newsID=2886">Asus A6J laptop</a>. It was one of the first laptops available with a dual core CPU (Core Duo, not Core 2 Duo) and decently powerful graphics (ATI X1600).<br/>
The A6J  is very dated now and weighing in at 2.85kg, its not very portable by today&rsquo;s standard (considering my <a href="/2011/12/toshiba-portege-z830.html">Toshiba Portege</a> weighs just 1.13kg).<br/>
A couple of years after I bought it, I got sick of carrying it around, so I bought an Asus EeePc as a replacement for uni, so the A6J stayed at home and was rarely used &ndash; it was just a spare for a long time.</p>

<p>Up until recently, I was using I used it as a (stationary) desktop replacement at work but I now have a new job where I am provided a  Macbook Pro so this old machine is now spare once again. This with the recent release of <a href="http://xbmc.org/natethomas/2012/03/24/xbmc-11-0-eden/">XBMC 11 Eden</a>, I thought I may as well re-purpose it as a permanent HTPC.</p>

<p>I considered quite a few options, such as running Arch Linux, OpenElec or Ubuntu with XBMC installed, or going with the recently improved XBMCbuntu (formerly known as XBMC Live).</p>

<h2>XBMCbuntu</h2>

<p>I downloaded the iso and had a bit of a play. I love how it boots directly into XBMC without the need to startup Unity or anything like that, although it does let you exit to the login screen and select either &ldquo;XBMCbuntu&rdquo; (LXDE) or &ldquo;OpenBox&rdquo; which is nice.</p>

<p>Once it had booted, it behaved so slow! I figured it mustn&rsquo;t have the correct drivers installed, so I tried to use the restricted drivers from the repo and after hitting quite a few problems I consulted the AMD site.<br/>
The <a href="http://support.amd.com/us/gpudownload/linux/Legacy/Pages/radeon_linux.aspx?type=2.4.1&amp;amp;product=2.4.1.3.12&amp;amp;lang=English">AMD site explains</a> that my ATI X1600 is now &ldquo;legacy&rdquo; and is supported by the ATI Catalyst 9.3 proprietary linux driver.<br/>
So I downloaded that and yet again hit a bunch of other issues.</p>

<p>I spent a fair portion of the day battling with this and couldn&rsquo;t help but think back to how easy Ubuntu Desktop handled all this, so I thought I&rsquo;d just give that another go.</p>

<h2>Ubuntu Desktop + XBMC</h2>

<p>I downloaded the Ubuntu 11.10 iso and installed that over the top of XBMCbuntu and configured the user account as &lsquo;xbmc&rsquo; and to automatically login at startup.<br/>
I then followed the <a href="http://wiki.xbmc.org/index.php?title=Installing_XBMC_for_Linux">instructions to install XBMC from their PPA</a>. I did a quick update, installed SSH, reconfigured grub to auto-boot in 1 second (instead of 10) and rebooted the machine.</p>

<p>When I launched XBMC, it was perfect! It was very snappy and there was no lag whatsoever.<br/>
I noticed that the power menu was missing the shutdown options that were in XBMCbuntu and that the suspend option did not work.<br/>
After a bit if research, I found a <a href="http://wiki.xbmc.org/index.php?title=HOW-TO:Suspend_and_wake_in_Ubuntu">wiki page</a> that explains how to modify <code>policykit</code> to allow xbmc access to all the power functions.<br/>
With this change, shutdown, suspend and hibernate were all working great.</p>

<p>I had already configured Wake-On-Lan in the past, so all that I needed to do was setup the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.xbmc.android.remote&amp;amp;feature=search_result#?t=W251bGwsMSwxLDEsIm9yZy54Ym1jLmFuZHJvaWQucmVtb3RlIl0.">Android XBMC remote app</a> on my phone. After configuring the app with the laptops IP address, MAC address, etc. I was now able to use the &ldquo;Turn your XBMC&rsquo;s Power On&rdquo; button from the mobile app to fire up the laptop.<br/>
Of course to actually allow control of XBMC I needed to go into the settings screen and enable control via HTTP, etc.</p>

<p>So now I can power up the laptop and shut it down from my phone, but when it boots, I am brought into a Unity environment. In the past I would add XBMC to the startup applications, but with XBMC Eden, there is a better way.<br/>
XBMC Eden adds it self to the choice of desktop environments from the login screen (in other words, you get a choice: Unity or straight into XBMC like the live cd).<br/>
Unfortunately it doesn&rsquo;t remember the last choice with XBMC, so if I boot straight into it and then shut it down, next time it will still automatically boot in to Unity.</p>

<p>I then came across an <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/AutoLogin#For_Ubuntu_10.04_.28Lucid_Lynx.29">Ubuntu community page</a> that pointed in the direction the the LightDM config file. (LightDM is the thing that manages the login screen).<br/>
I opened <code>/etc/lightdm/lightdm.conf</code> and saw this line:</p>

<p><code>
user-session=ubuntu
</code></p>

<p>I replaced the <code>ubuntu</code> part of this line with <code>XBMC</code>, rebooted and low and behold, it booted straight into XBMC!</p>

<p>I now have a fully functional HTPC that I can completely control from my phone.<br/>
The only things left to do now are configure my media sources, install some plugins and maybe play with some new skins.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
