<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pidgin | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/pidgin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-12T14:34:55+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GTalkSMS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/gtalksms.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-08T10:41:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/gtalksms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
Continuing on from my last post, I found another great use for Pidgin!<br /><br />GTalkSMS is an Android app that turns your phone into a chat bot.<br />Here is an extract from the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/gtalksms/">GTalkSMS website</a>:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-size: x-small;"><i>GTalkSMS enables you to <b>control your android phone through GTalk/XMPP</b> (send/receive SMS, make calls, locate your phone, etc.). It can be  useful for those who prefer typing sms on a real keyboard. The app also  notifies you about new "events" on the phone, like a new text message  (SMS) or an incoming call.</i></span></blockquote><br />Although initially skeptical about security (it has the same functions as a would-be trojan) you have to be buddies with the bot to talk to it, so here is what I did...<br /><br /><br /><b>Basic Setup:</b> <br /><ul><li>Downloaded and installed GTalkSMS from the <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.googlecode.gtalksms">market</a></li><li>Created a google account for GTalkSMS</li><li>Configured Pidgin with my personal gmail account (obviously) </li><li>Added this new account as a buddy on my personal gmail account</li><li>Configured GTalkSMS to send notifications to my personal gmail account</li></ul><br /><b>Basic Usage:</b> <br /><br />With this done, once I start the bot, it will send me a instant message when I get an SMS, phone call or the battery state changes.<br /><br />What is even better is that if I want to reply to a recently received SMS, I can send the bot an instant message like this:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">reply:Hey, I got your message</span></blockquote><br />If I want to initiate an SMS to someone else, I can send this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">sms:mymate:Hey, how you goin?</span></blockquote><br />That will lookup <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">mymate</span> in my phonebook and send the SMS to them.<br />If you have multiple people with the same name, you can search your phonebook using this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">contact:john</span></blockquote><br />This will list all the <i>John's</i> then you can just copy and paste the phone number you want in place of the name, like this:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">sms:04041111111:Hey John!</span></blockquote><br /><b>Doing more:</b> <br /><br />There are <a href="http://code.google.com/p/gtalksms/wiki/FeaturesAndCommands">heaps of commands</a> available and you can get a list of them all at any time with this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">help:all</span></blockquote><br />Some other cool commands allow you to change your ringer volume, take a photo, share clipboards, get geolocation, launch a given URL in the browser and lots more.<br /><br />It also has some options to make GTalkSMS start automatically when the phone boots, or when it is charging, or when its on wifi.<br />I personally only want this connected while I'm in front of my pc, so I have it set to start when charging and stop when not charging anymore (I use a USB charging dock at my desk).<br /><br />One other noteworthy feature is the "Incoming SMS" setting "<span style="font-size: small;"><span style="color: black;">In separated conversations</span></span>". When you receive an sms, not only does the bot send you an IM, but it will start a new "chat room" for that particular contact and send you an invite. From within this chat room, you dont need to worry about sending commands, whatever you send in there will be sent as an sms to that client. It makes it look seamlessly like any other chat.<br /><br /><br /><b>Pidgin fun:</b><br /><b><br /></b><br />As you may already know, I like Pidgin because of its configurability.<br />I have Pidgin using the libnotify plugin, which means I get the fancy Ubuntu notifications from Pidgin, but I soon realised there are too many notifications by default (everytime a buddy signs in or out is a bit much with 4 chat accounts signed in at once!) - so I turned those notifications off.<br /><br />But! I wanted these notifications to see when my phone is available to chat, so I set up some little recurring buddy pounces:<br /><ol><li>When my GTalkSMS account signs in, execute this command: <br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">notify-send -i "/usr/share/pixmaps/pidgin/emblems/scalable/bot.svg" "Droid online" "Your Android is now contactable via GTalkSMS"</span></blockquote></li><li>When my GTalkSMS account signs out, execute this command: <br /><blockquote style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">notify-send -i "/usr/share/pixmaps/pidgin/emblems/scalable/unavailable.svg" "Droid offline" "Your Android has now signed off GTalkSMS" </blockquote></li></ol><br />Now when I dock my phone, it starts charging, GTalkSMS starts up and signs in and I get this notification appear:<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PFO4tCzM4hU/TmhBzgUoyxI/AAAAAAAAACk/l2VJNWYCIF0/s1600/online.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="173" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PFO4tCzM4hU/TmhBzgUoyxI/AAAAAAAAACk/l2VJNWYCIF0/s320/online.png" width="320" /></a></div><br /><br />Then when I pull it off the dock, GTalkSMS signs out and I get this notification:<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Xwq4VMTPyNw/TmhB6BYJfrI/AAAAAAAAACo/Hu2KWVTrADw/s1600/offline.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="173" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Xwq4VMTPyNw/TmhB6BYJfrI/AAAAAAAAACo/Hu2KWVTrADw/s320/offline.png" width="320" /></a></div><br /><br />Note: The notify-send command is available from the <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">libnotify-bin</span> package, which can be installed in Ubuntu with this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">sudo apt-get install libnotify-bin</span></blockquote>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meta-contacts in Pidgin]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/meta-contacts-in-pidgin.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-03T00:18:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/meta-contacts-in-pidgin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
<a href="http://pidgin.im/">Pidgin</a> is my IM client of choice, its one of the first things I replace in a stock installation of Ubuntu.<br />I chose Pidgin not because of a slick UI but because it has some really nice features!<br /><br />The two features that stand out the most in my opinion are the "buddy pounces" and the many available plugins:<br /><br /><b>Buddy pounces</b><b>:</b><br />For those that don't know about pounces, they are little predefined actions that can be triggered upon some configurable event, such as <i>"when &lt;SomeContact&gt; returns from away status, open a conversation window"</i>, or <i>"when &lt;SomeContact&gt; signs on, send them a predefined message"</i>.<br /><br /><b>Plugins:</b><br />Not only does Pidgin come with lots of plugins by default, but there are a lot of <a href="http://developer.pidgin.im/wiki/ThirdPartyPlugins">third party plugins</a> available too.<br />There are basic ones that offer a more robust and configurable way of notifying you of messages, etc and some more fun ones like "psychic mode" - which listens for when a new contact starts typing a message to you and pops up a convo window before they have even sent it.<br /><br /><b>Meta-contacts:</b><br />The one thing that I missed from other IM clients was meta-contacts.<br />For example, at any one time I have Pidgin signed into my Google chat, MSN and Facebook chat accounts and for those friends of mine that have an account on all three platforms, they appear 3 times in my buddy list.<br />With meta-contacts you can collapse those 3 contacts into just one.<br /><br />Well, it turns out this feature has been in Pidgin for quite a while, I just never noticed as its just not quite as obvious as with other clients.<br /><br /><b>How to use meta-contacts in Pidgin:</b><br />To use this feature, all you have to do is right-mouse click on the contact and click "expand" and drag and drop other contacts under the newly expanded name.<br />You should put the most common account at the top as that is the account is used by default when you double click the contact.<br /><br />Even though these features aren't exactly ground breaking, when you get used to having them there it becomes a little harder to go back to clients without them.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
