<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: github | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/github/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-19T14:16:09+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git + Hub = GitHub]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/02/git-hub-github.html"/>
    <updated>2012-02-20T02:37:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/02/git-hub-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
As mentioned in a <a href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/code-review-workflow-with-github.html" target="_blank">previous post</a>, we use <a href="http://scottchacon.com/2011/08/31/github-flow.html" target="_blank">GitHub-Flow</a> at work and I really like it.<br />In essence, it involves doing work in feature branches, while maintaining an <i>always deployable</i> <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span> branch, then opening a pull request to merge a new feature / bugfix into <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span>, which provides a great mechanism for code review / sign-off.<br /><br />So a fairly typical situation would be as follows:<br /><ul><li>Bug found in app</li><li>Create an issue on GitHub with description, assignee, etc.</li><li>Create a new branch off master for the fix</li><li>Code it up, test locally, etc.</li><li>Push branch to GitHub </li><li>Open pull request to merge back into master</li><li>Get review / sign-off inside of the pull request</li><li>Deploy </li></ul>When a pull request is opened on GitHub, it automatically creates an issue for that pull request, which would normally be helpful, but we already created an issue when the bug was discovered.<br />So now we have 2 issues and 1 pull request. What's nice is that if I push more commits to that branch, it will appear in the pull request automatically, but not the initial issue.<br /><br />After looking into this, it seems (AFAIK) GitHub do not provide a way of attaching a pull request to an existing issue via the site, but they do provide that functionality via their API.<br /><br />That is when I discovered <a href="http://defunkt.io/hub/" target="_blank"><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">Hub</span></a>.<br /><a href="https://github.com/defunkt/hub" target="_blank"><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">Hub</span></a> is a wrapper for <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">git</span> and while it adds more power to alot of the standard git commands, hub adds one command that is really useful for me:<br /><br /><blockquote class="tr_bq" style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">git pull-request -i 49</blockquote><br />This basically means<i> "Open a pull request to merge the current branch into master and attach the pull request to issue 49"</i>.<br /><br />This means that the initial bug description, the commits, the review conversation and the merge are all encapsulated in a single issue - fantastic!<br />I don't know why this isn't built in to the web interface (or maybe it is and I just don't know how).
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code review workflow with GitHub]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/code-review-workflow-with-github.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-18T10:06:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/code-review-workflow-with-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
The more I use Git, the more I love it and less I prefer my once trusty SVN.<br /><br />A while back I read the book <i>"<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1430218339?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=prgi-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1430218339">Pro Git</a>"</i> by <a href="http://twitter.com/#%21/chacon">Scott Chacon</a>.<br />The book provides a really good explanation of how Git works and how to use it effectively.<br />I then found that this book is <a href="http://progit.org/">available online</a> for free and it is now a commonly visited bookmark for me.<br /><br />Recently my boss sent me a link to a <a href="http://scottchacon.com/2011/08/31/github-flow.html">blog post</a> by Scott Chacon that explains the Git workflow that is used at GitHub on a daily basis as we are going to give it a go for our own projects.<br /><br />In the post, Scott contrasts this to the commonly known "<a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">Git-Flow</a>" and describes how they are both good, but Git-Flow is alot more involved, where the aptly known "GitHub-Flow" is a lot simpler and therefore easier to follow.<br /><br />For full details, I highly recommend reading the post but  basically it involves keeping a <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span> branch that is always stable (and deployable) and using topic branches for development. Once a topic branch is tested locally you open a pull request to have others review it and merge it in to <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span>.<br /><br />Using pull requests within a single repository for code reviews are really useful!<br />It allows a discussion thread to take place, commenting on individual lines of code and keeps a history of the rational for any changes.<br /><br />A good aspect of this approach is that these topic branches can be pushed to GitHub constantly as it will not affect anyone else's work, and allows the team to have visibility of who is working on what by simply looking at the branch list page.<br />This of course means that your branches should be descriptively named.<br /><br />We have been using this workflow for a little while now and have felt compelled to make a small modification.<br />We have a staging environment which closely matches the production environment and is externally available to show clients new features, etc.<br />To cater for this we have introduced an additional long-term branch called "<span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">staging</span>".<br /><br />This doesn't affect our existing workflow for the majority of cases, but every now and then we will merge <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span> into <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">staging</span>, then the topic branch into <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">staging</span> to test/preview/etc. (without the need for pull requests/code review). Once the change is tested/previewed in <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">staging</span> and proven to be good, a pull request is opened for the topic branch to be merged into <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span> (as per usual).<br /><br />One thing to note here is that it's the topic branch to be merged and not the <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">staging</span> branch. Although in most cases this wont matter, if multiple merges from <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">staging</span> into <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">master</span> occur it can become confusing. Also the merge commit description will contain "<span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">repo/staging</span>" instead of something more descriptive, like "<span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">repo/bundler-upgrade</span>".<br /><br />I have really enjoyed using this workflow and it seems to be working quite well so far. In the process of implementing this you really get to see how useful GitHub can be with using pull requests for code reviews and the branch list and network graph features for visualising not only your own progress, but the entire project too.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
