<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: parallel port | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/parallel-port/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-14T23:27:35+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby + parallel port + LEDs]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/10/ruby-parallel-port-leds.html"/>
    <updated>2011-10-10T03:49:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/10/ruby-parallel-port-leds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
In the initial R&amp;D stages for our <a href="http://tank.stevenocchipinti.com/">Tank Project</a> we have to work out the most suitable way to interface from software to hardware - which I have never done before!<br /><br /><br /><b>The parallel port</b><br /><br />One of those options is to use the parallel port, which allows us 8 data pins that we can use for controlling motors, etc.<br />The layout of a parallel port is quite easy, there are 8 "D" pins for data with 8 matching "Ground" pins (shown in green below).<br /><br /><div style="padding: 32px; text-align: center;"><a href="http://linuxgazette.net/118/misc/chong/parallel_port_diagram.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">  <img border="0" height="214" src="http://linuxgazette.net/118/misc/chong/parallel_port_diagram.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><b>The test rig</b><br /><br />As the output from the parallel port is about 5 volts, I though LED's were a suitable was of testing this out, so I went searching through our garage to find a parallel cable from an old printer and a bunch of LED's.<br />I found a bunch of tristate LED's - tristates have 3 legs instead of 2 and provide 2 different colors depending on which legs have power to them.<br />For example, if the circuit connects the left leg and the middle leg, it produces green light, whereas the right leg and middle leg produce red light.<br />Soldering 4 of these LEDs to a board meant I could join all the middle legs together which would be what I connect the ground wire from the parallel port to and the other 8 legs to the 8 data wires.<br /><br /><br /><b>The software</b><br /><br />In order to control when each of the data pins has power to it or not, you simply have to write 8 bits (a byte) to the parallel port where each bit corresponds to a data pin.<br />In linux this is quite simple as you can write to <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">/dev/port</span> just like any other file.<br />To test this out, I wrote a little Ruby script to play a fancy little sequence a few times. The code is quite simple considering some <a href="http://yueda.issp.u-tokyo.ac.jp/weda/ruby/parport.rb">other examples</a> on the net:<br /><br /><script src="https://gist.github.com/1274548.js"></script><br /><br /><b>The fun part!</b> <br /><br />So my computer doesn't have a parallel port, but we have some older machines that do. So I found an old pc and booted off a linux live distro that has ruby, plugged in the cable with the LEDs on it, and ran my script, and this is what happens: <br /><div style="padding: 32px; text-align: center;"><embed allowfullscreen="true" src="http://img546.imageshack.us/flvplayer.swf?f=Pjch" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="300" wmode="transparent"></embed></div><b>The conclusion</b><br /><br />This is the first time I have ever written a program that uses hardware, albeit really basic hardware, but this has a lot of potential.<br />Instead of turning on lights, this small current could trigger relays to do more exciting things, or in our case power transistors using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulse-width_modulation">PWM</a> to control motor speed for our tank - and its so simple!
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
