<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Email | Steven Occhipinti]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/email/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-28T02:20:32+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spam Defence]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/spam-defence.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-07T11:14:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/spam-defence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
For quite a long time I used to use Yahoo! Mail.<br />Even though I was lucky enough to get an invite for Gmail in its early stages, Yahoo! Mail had (IMO) one killer feature: <i>Address Guard</i><br /><br />The idea behind <i>Address Guard</i> was simple, you make your primary email address, say <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">john.smith@yahoo.com</span>, and then a secondary <i>"base name"</i>, such as <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">johno007</span>.<br />This <i>base name</i> was not just another email address, infact all mail sent to <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">johno007@yahoo.com</span> would get dropped.<br />Instead, use that base name to create an unlimited number of <i>"disposable addresses"</i>, such as <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">johno007-facebook@yahoo.com</span>, etc.<br /><br />The idea was that if you follow the simple 3 click process (settings -&gt; addressGaurd -&gt; add new address!) to create a new disposable email address every time you signed up for a new website, if ever they spammed you, you simply delete that address and they wont be able to bother you any more - brilliant!<br /><br />I avoided Gmail because they didn't have the same <i>"whitelist"</i> approach to email addresses, but when I bought my domain name and started using Google Apps for email, I decided to use Gmail as my primary email provider.<br />Naturally this forced me to look for a similar way to defend again spam (albeit Gmails spam filtering is quite good).<br /><br />Google Apps provides <i>"nicknames"</i>, which works in much the same way, you can have an unlimited number of aliases for an account, except the process was a bit longer (settings -&gt; manage domain -&gt; users -&gt; Your user -&gt; Add a nickname) and I got too lazy for that after a little while.<br />I still use nicknames for certain things, but not for every website I sign up for.<br /><br />That's when I discovered the + symbol in Gmail. Unlike Yahoo! Mail that uses the <i>"whitelist"</i> approach (only addresses you created will accept mail), you can use Gmail with a <i>"blacklist"</i> approach (all addresses accept mail unless you block them).<br /><br />Assume your email address is <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">john.smith@gmail.com</span>, you can append a + and then any (valid) characters you like to the end, such as <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">john.smith+facebook@gmail.com</span> and it will still get delivered.<br /><br />If some rogue website starts sending spam to <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">john.smith+dodgysite@gmail.com</span>, then you can go into the Gmail settings and setup a filter to delete all mail that is sent to: <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">john.smith+dodgysite@gmail.com</span>.<br /><br />I don't think it's quite as nice as <i>Address Guard</i>, but it is a bit more convenient because there is no set up. The biggest downside is that quite a few websites consider an email address to be invalid if it has a + symbol in it, but most are fine.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
