<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: android | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/android/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-17T17:34:29+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Safe mode" on the Samsung Galaxy S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2013/05/safe-mode-on-samsung-galaxy-s3.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-12T04:36:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2013/05/safe-mode-on-samsung-galaxy-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had some trouble with my Samsung Galaxy S3. I&rsquo;m still not sure what caused it, but quite frequently, it would completely freeze up, even after a fresh reboot. It may have been a dodgy app, or something deeper in android, but in the process of fixing it, I was introduced to &ldquo;<em>safe mode</em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>&ldquo;<em>Safe mode</em>&rdquo; here behaves like safe mode in Windows. It basically lets you use your phone just like normal, but without starting the usual plethora of background processes. You can still get to your settings, apps and files, but things won&rsquo;t start automatically.</p>

<p>To enter safe mode on the Galaxy S3 is really simple:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>1. Restart the phone<br/>2. While it is booting up (and you see the Samsung logo),<br/><br/>   simply hold the volume down button</p></blockquote></p>

<p>When it boots, you should have the stock wallpaper, your shortcuts will be gone and you should see a little watermark in the bottom left corner that says &ldquo;<em>Safe mode</em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-AJ8LJPOQQPM/UY8ZnFfsA-I/AAAAAAAABPM/4yaTDxpxyH8/Screenshot_2013-05-12-09-41-12.png">http://lh4.ggpht.com/-AJ8LJPOQQPM/UY8ZnFfsA-I/AAAAAAAABPM/4yaTDxpxyH8/Screenshot_2013-05-12-09-41-12.png</a>"></p>

<p>From here you can do everything like normal, browse the net, make calls, etc. but more importantly, you can uninstall dodgy apps, change settings, even factory reset the device.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Samsung Galaxy S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/08/samsung-galaxy-s3.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-21T12:50:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/08/samsung-galaxy-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
At the end of June this year, I upgraded from a HTC Desire HD to a Samsung Galaxy S3, so I thought after a couple of months of having my new phone I should write up a (really long) post on what stood out for me.<br /><br /><br /><b>The positive</b> <br /><br />The <b>screen and form factor</b> is awesome! Due to the plastic body and the thin shape, this phone is really light and slips into your pocket nicely. The massive 4.8" screen really shines when watching videos and browsing the web. I regularly watch screencasts on my phone and the 1280x720 resolution gives me plenty of detail. The colour contrast is a lot higher than my previous phone, which makes the blacks look really deep and videos stand out nicely. The marketing video that the phone comes with does demo it off quite well!<br /><br />The <b>battery </b>is fairly good. My requirement for battery life is that I can use it all day and by the time I get home / go to bed, it hasn't died. Not a high expectation, I know, but these days its hard to expect more. This phone meets that requirement quite easily. On the days I don't use my phone much, I get home after a days work with more than 50% remaining (which is huge compared to my last phone!) and on the days I use it quite heavily, I get home to about 30%-40% which easily lasts me the rest of the night. My usage generally includes syncing gmail, facebook, twitter, weather, RSS reader, work email (during peak hours), I am generally connected to wifi most of the time and I regularly browse the web and watch videos / listen to podcasts during my commute.<br /><br />The general<b> responsiveness</b> is miles ahead of my last phone too! Day-to-day usage is smooth and rarely experience any lag. This will be improved even more when Jellybean is released (rumoured to be soon!).<br /><br /><b>"Smart Stay" </b>is a new innovative feature from Samsung where just before the screen is about to timeout and turn off, the phone will take a photo of you with the front-facing camera and use face (or eye) detection to work out if you're still looking at it. If you are, it will keep it on for another minute or so, if you're not, then it will dim the screen and check again soon after, which then will actually turn it off.<br />This is to avoid that randomly-scrolling-to-avoid-the-screen-turning-off trick that most people will do when reading a long article. Thankfully, this feature is quite effective and I haven't needed to do that for a while, although it doesn't work very well in the dark!<br /><br />In the settings, there is a section called <b>"Motion"</b>. I won't go through all of the options, as there are about 10 different ones, but some are quite handy. By far the best one IMHO is <b>"Direct call"</b>, which lets you directly call a contact whose call log details, contact details or message details are displayed on the screen by simply putting the phone to your ear from that screen. Feels very natural.<br />Another nice one is <b>"Smart alert"</b>, which will give a little vibration when you pick it up from a stationary location if you have a missed call or sms.<br /><br />The <b>camera</b> on this phone is not too bad either. Obviously it will never replace my dSLR, but it has some nice features that even my dSLR doesn't have. The burst fire mode is really quick, but Samsung have introduced a feature called <b>"best shot"</b>, which will analyse each of the photos you took in the burst and pick the ones it thinks turned out the best, based on focus and face detection. You can adjust what was picked, and then the others are automatically discarded (saves you having to go through the 14 bad ones and delete them later).<br />The camera has a <b>built-in HDR</b> mode which works quite well too and the <b>photo editor</b> provides heaps of enhancements and corrections, including red-eye reduction, color balance, cropping, etc.<br /><br />Another nice feature is found in the video player, it has a <b>"pop-out"</b> button! This means that if you're in the middle of a video and you wanted to quickly google something, or reply to an sms, you can just pop out the video, which turns the full screen player into a small, floating, always on top window that you can drag around, do what you need to do, and then make it full screen again. Not something that I've needed to use very often, but on the rare occasion I have, it's been quite nice.<br /><br />I use my calendar religiously and on my older HTC, the default app looked nice, but didn't have many features. I ended up swapping it out for <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=netgenius.bizcal&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">Business Calendar Free</a> just so I could get a month view with text, instead of indicators.<br />The stock Samsung calendar, <b>S Planner</b>, however is not too bad! It integrates with their S Memo, which I don't use, but comes with a good number of viewing options, my favourites being their month view and analogue week view. It also has a nice <b>"Quick add" </b>feature that lets you enter "Dinner at Nandos tomorrow 7:30pm" and it does what you'd expect. This doesn't support anywhere near as much as Google Calendar does, but its better than nothing!<br /><br />I lashed out and bought an <b>official Samsung Desktop Dock</b>, and comparing this to my cheap eBay special I bought for my HTC, not only does it look quite nice, but it automatically launches the desktop clock app when I dock it and after 5 minutes it dims the screen and hides the other UI elements other than the clock. I like this feature a lot because I otherwise don't have a clock in my room, so its really handy for me!<br /><br /><br />As with all things, there are pro's and con's. Here are some of the things I don't like. <br /><br /><br /><b>The negative</b><br /><br />Android have decided to <b>remove USB Mass Storage mode</b> (my biggest pet hate with Android right now!) This leaves you with 3 alternative options for copying files to and from the device: Media Transfer Protocol (MTP), Camera mode or using an app such as <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.samsung.swift.app.kiesair&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">Kies Air</a> or <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=xcxin.filexpert&amp;feature=search_result#?t=W251bGwsMSwxLDEsInhjeGluLmZpbGV4cGVydCJd" target="_blank">File Expert</a>.<br />MTP and Camera mode both don't give you access to all the directories on the phone, but for just transferring media it should be ok. Note that MTP will work out of the box with Windows, but if you run Mac or Linux like me, you will need to install software to get it to work (and Linux is a pain for this!).<br />The reason for this change is because USB Mass Storage mode will mean you have to unmount the partition from the system in order to mount it to the computer, whereas MTP will allow you to access it in both places at once, but its slower and requires software.<br />For phones like the Galaxy Nexus, this makes sense as there is only one partition, but with the S3, I would like to see the option of just unmounting the memory card (with is separate from the system storage) and allow that to work with USB Mass Storage mode.<br /><br />Another annoying thing I have found with this phone is sometimes the <b>home screen will randomly die</b>. This causes lag while all the widgets reinitialise themselves. It doesn't happen often, but when it does, its annoying considering its a simple software issue. Hopefully this is fixed with Jellybean release!<br /><br />On a related note, I find the random delay between pressing the <b>unlock button</b> and the screen actually turning on to be annoying too, considering my older HTC was basically instantaneous everytime, this phone seems to vary quite a lot. I find myself pressing the button while its still in my pocket, just so by the time I have it in front of me, the screen is ready.<br /><br />A couple of other minor things include the <b>notification LED</b> being really bright, which is ok, but while the phone is docked my bedside, it will light up the entire room quite easily. This is kind of funny considering "smart stay" doesn't work well at night. Maybe instead of just green and red, the LED should have also included an IR LED for that.<br />Not only is the LED really bright, but when the battery becomes fully charged, it will turn on the screen and popup a notification, which is also not very nice when I'm trying to sleep.<br />I know most of you are probably thinking a solution would be to turn it off at night, but I <a href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/xkcd-beyondpod.html" target="_blank">scheduled my phone to download podcasts</a> during these hours with <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=mobi.beyondpod&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">BeyondPod</a> - I think the pro's outweigh the con's in this situation.<br /><br />Also minor, but there is <b>no stock flashlight app</b>, which I wanted to put in the lock screen shortcuts. It does come with a 2x1 widget, but to get a shortcut on the lock screen, I ended up downloading one of the million flashlight apps out there.<br /><br />Speaking of widgets, the HTC widgets were really nice, but I find the <b>widgets</b> that came with the Samsung are not quite as useful, luckily they are in abundance on the play store too!<br /><br /><br /><b>The other stuff</b><br /><br />Here are some other noteworthy things which I haven't really made up my mind if I like yet or not.<br /><br />The music player has a feature called <b>"Music Square"</b> and I love the idea of it, but I'm not sure how effective it is. Basically you index your music library and it categorises each of your songs into 2 scales: <i>'Exciting</i> to <i>Calm'</i> and <i>'Passionate</i> to <i>Joyful</i>'. These two scales make up the axes of the music square and by tapping where your mood is will play those types of songs. It's a great idea and I need to experiment with it more to see how effective it is.<br /><br />A lot of the features in the phone are <b>voice activated</b>. For example, you can say <i>'answer'</i> or <i>'reject'</i> when it is ringing (as long as the ringtone isn't too loud); <i>'snooze'</i> or <i>'stop'</i> when the alarm is going off (as long as thats not too loud); <i>'smile'</i>, <i>'cheese'</i>, <i>'capture'</i> or <i>'shoot'</i> to take a photo (as long as your close enough for the phone to hear you); <i>'next'</i>, <i>'previous'</i>, <i>'pause'</i>, <i>'play'</i>, <i>'volume'</i>, etc. to control your music or the radio (as long as thats not too loud either).<br />As you can see, the usefulness of these features are dependant on the environment.<br /><br /><b>S Voice</b> is Samsung's answer to Siri, and even the UI's look similar, but while its great in theory, I think the most useful thing about Siri on the iPhone or S Voice on the Galaxy would be SMS/email dictation, but that is the one thing these features don't work that well for, at least for me anyway - maybe its just my voice!<br /><br /><br /><b>The conclusion</b><br /><br />In the end I am very happy with my new phone, it is leaps and bounds above my old phone, its really responsive other than the random home screen lag and unlock button delay, it has some nice new innovative features and is a joy to use.<br />Also, with the Jellybean release (hopefully) around the corner, it can only get better.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rooting the HTC Desire HD & Cyanogenmod 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/rooting-htc-desire-hd-cyanogenmod-7.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-31T07:10:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/rooting-htc-desire-hd-cyanogenmod-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
At the end of last year my <i>HTC Desire HD</i> got its firmware upgrade to the new version of <i>HTC Sense</i> - the same version that the <i>HTC Sensation</i> is running.<br />At the time I thought it was quite cool, having shortcuts on the lock screen is great and the new eye candy looks pretty nice too.<br /><br />But there were some very unwelcome changes with this new version too... lag and poor battery life!<br />I generally keep my phone on charge at work, so I didn't think this would bother me, but it got so bad that if I went out after work, by the time I got home it was flat (from 6pm to later that night). Even swiping between home screens would lag! So I figured it was time for a new phone, but in the meantime I thought I may as well experiment with rooting and other OS's.<br /><br />To root the Desire HD is quite simple. The first thing to do is go get the "<i><a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=1259821" target="_blank"><u>Advanced Ace Hack Kit</u></a></i>" from the XDA Forums. In the zip file is all the tools you need to run the hack and most importantly, the aptly named "<span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">effen-manual.html</span>", which is <i>very</i> important!<br /><br />The manual explains everything you need to know, but the first step is checking that the version of android that you are running can be exploited.<br />I had software  version <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">3.12.405.1</span>, which judging by the <i>effen manual</i>, the hack tool can automatically downgrade to version <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">2.50.405.2</span> where there exists a flaw that can be exploited to give you root access.<br />Keep in mind that doing this will wipe your phone, so backup <i>everything</i>.<br /><br />The <i>effen manual</i> also explains how to setup your computer to enable the hack tool to work properly. There are very few steps for linux which was great!<br /><br />If you follow the instructions correctly, you will then have a stock standard install of an older version of HTC Sense. There are some advantages to having root access such as apps like titanium backup, ad blockers, etc. but the real fun comes from installing new Android ROMs.<br /><br />I looked at 2 third party ROMs, the first was <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.com/" target="_blank">Cyanogen Mod</a> and the second was <a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=840040" target="_blank">Android Revolution</a>.<br /><br />Android Revolution looks pretty good. Visually it looks and behaves just like HTC Sense but they have made lots of improvements under the hood which in turn increases performance and battery life. As good as this looked, I haven't actually tried this option yet. Instead, I opted to go for a bigger change of scenery and give Cyanogen Mod a go.<br /><br /><br />Cyanogen Mod does not look like HTC Sense at all. Instead it is based on stock standard Android 2.3. They have then implemented a slew of changes that come as default, such as an audio equaliser, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.adw.launcher&amp;hl=en" target="_blank">ADWLauncher</a>, the super-user app, a completely customisable button widget in the notification bar, customizable lock screens and a pretty cool torch app that lets you over charge the LEDs for super brightness!<br />This mod also lets you overclock the hardware, put limiters in place and lots of other options I was not used to seeing in the HTC Sense ROM.<br /><br />The 2 most important advantages of this change are that the UI is now quick and responsive again, I now have complete control over which effects are used and things like how long the animations should last, etc. and I have the best battery life I've ever had with this phone - I can now use the phone pretty heavily all day without needing a charge until I go to bed!<br /><br />Very happy with it now and it should keep me tied over until the Samsung Galaxy SIII is released :)
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[XKCD + BeyondPod]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/xkcd-beyondpod.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-04T04:10:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/03/xkcd-beyondpod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
On my Android phone, I use an app called "<a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=mobi.beyondpod&amp;hl=en%20" target="_blank">BeyondPod</a>". <br /><br />BeyondPod is great because unlike <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.google.android.apps.reader&amp;feature=search_result#?t=W251bGwsMSwxLDEsImNvbS5nb29nbGUuYW5kcm9pZC5hcHBzLnJlYWRlciJd" target="_blank">Google Reader</a> and <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.alphonso.pulse&amp;feature=search_result#?t=W251bGwsMSwxLDEsImNvbS5hbHBob25zby5wdWxzZSJd" target="_blank">Pulse</a> (which are other great RSS readers), BeyondPod will download video and audio podcasts on a schedule.<br /><br />What this means for me, is that at 2:30 AM, my phone will use my home ADSL2's off-peak downloads and fetch a bunch of regular podcasts so when I wake up and make my way into work, I will have all the latest episodes of my favourite shows to watch and listen to on the train.<br /><br />One of the feeds that I'm subscribed to is <a href="http://xkcd.com/%20" target="_blank">XKCD</a>. If you look at the comics online, you probably already know that if hover your mouse over the image, you get to see an extra message about the comic.<br /><br />On Google Reader, you can tap and hold the image and use the menu to get to the tooltip, but with BeyondPod, there is no such option.<br /><br />This means that the tooltip is actually included in the <a href="http://xkcd.com/atom.xml" target="_blank">feed</a>, so I thought it would be pretty easy to write a little proxy that pulls out the "title=" attribute and appends it to the body.<br /><br />Before I started coding, I thought that surely someone would have already done this, so after a quick Google search I came across a <a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.info?_id=upJ5TUni3BGUZU9yLO2fWQ" target="_blank">Yahoo! Pipe</a> from "<a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/person.info?guid=D4HQ7VIJ2YNE6NZRH3VHJOBREA">Benjamin Cook</a>" that does exactly that.<br /><br />Ben's Pipe appends a "&lt;br /&gt;" and then the tooltip, but the "&lt;br /&gt;" seems to be getting escaped, so I copied the pipe and removed the "&lt;br /&gt;" and the end result was exactly what I wanted.<br /><br />If you have a similar problem, you can add <a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.info?_id=61e54ab0572541bd03cd44f3e601482e" target="_blank">my version of the pipe</a> to your reader and here's what it'll look like: <br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-lErLdyOZLO8/T0XMYWJY6SI/AAAAAAAAADw/-yKGNhQwHgw/s1600/2012-02-23_16-14-04.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="320" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-lErLdyOZLO8/T0XMYWJY6SI/AAAAAAAAADw/-yKGNhQwHgw/s320/2012-02-23_16-14-04.jpg" width="192" /></a></div><br />
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GTalkSMS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/gtalksms.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-08T10:41:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/gtalksms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
Continuing on from my last post, I found another great use for Pidgin!<br /><br />GTalkSMS is an Android app that turns your phone into a chat bot.<br />Here is an extract from the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/gtalksms/">GTalkSMS website</a>:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-size: x-small;"><i>GTalkSMS enables you to <b>control your android phone through GTalk/XMPP</b> (send/receive SMS, make calls, locate your phone, etc.). It can be  useful for those who prefer typing sms on a real keyboard. The app also  notifies you about new "events" on the phone, like a new text message  (SMS) or an incoming call.</i></span></blockquote><br />Although initially skeptical about security (it has the same functions as a would-be trojan) you have to be buddies with the bot to talk to it, so here is what I did...<br /><br /><br /><b>Basic Setup:</b> <br /><ul><li>Downloaded and installed GTalkSMS from the <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.googlecode.gtalksms">market</a></li><li>Created a google account for GTalkSMS</li><li>Configured Pidgin with my personal gmail account (obviously) </li><li>Added this new account as a buddy on my personal gmail account</li><li>Configured GTalkSMS to send notifications to my personal gmail account</li></ul><br /><b>Basic Usage:</b> <br /><br />With this done, once I start the bot, it will send me a instant message when I get an SMS, phone call or the battery state changes.<br /><br />What is even better is that if I want to reply to a recently received SMS, I can send the bot an instant message like this:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">reply:Hey, I got your message</span></blockquote><br />If I want to initiate an SMS to someone else, I can send this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">sms:mymate:Hey, how you goin?</span></blockquote><br />That will lookup <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">mymate</span> in my phonebook and send the SMS to them.<br />If you have multiple people with the same name, you can search your phonebook using this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">contact:john</span></blockquote><br />This will list all the <i>John's</i> then you can just copy and paste the phone number you want in place of the name, like this:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">sms:04041111111:Hey John!</span></blockquote><br /><b>Doing more:</b> <br /><br />There are <a href="http://code.google.com/p/gtalksms/wiki/FeaturesAndCommands">heaps of commands</a> available and you can get a list of them all at any time with this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">help:all</span></blockquote><br />Some other cool commands allow you to change your ringer volume, take a photo, share clipboards, get geolocation, launch a given URL in the browser and lots more.<br /><br />It also has some options to make GTalkSMS start automatically when the phone boots, or when it is charging, or when its on wifi.<br />I personally only want this connected while I'm in front of my pc, so I have it set to start when charging and stop when not charging anymore (I use a USB charging dock at my desk).<br /><br />One other noteworthy feature is the "Incoming SMS" setting "<span style="font-size: small;"><span style="color: black;">In separated conversations</span></span>". When you receive an sms, not only does the bot send you an IM, but it will start a new "chat room" for that particular contact and send you an invite. From within this chat room, you dont need to worry about sending commands, whatever you send in there will be sent as an sms to that client. It makes it look seamlessly like any other chat.<br /><br /><br /><b>Pidgin fun:</b><br /><b><br /></b><br />As you may already know, I like Pidgin because of its configurability.<br />I have Pidgin using the libnotify plugin, which means I get the fancy Ubuntu notifications from Pidgin, but I soon realised there are too many notifications by default (everytime a buddy signs in or out is a bit much with 4 chat accounts signed in at once!) - so I turned those notifications off.<br /><br />But! I wanted these notifications to see when my phone is available to chat, so I set up some little recurring buddy pounces:<br /><ol><li>When my GTalkSMS account signs in, execute this command: <br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">notify-send -i "/usr/share/pixmaps/pidgin/emblems/scalable/bot.svg" "Droid online" "Your Android is now contactable via GTalkSMS"</span></blockquote></li><li>When my GTalkSMS account signs out, execute this command: <br /><blockquote style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">notify-send -i "/usr/share/pixmaps/pidgin/emblems/scalable/unavailable.svg" "Droid offline" "Your Android has now signed off GTalkSMS" </blockquote></li></ol><br />Now when I dock my phone, it starts charging, GTalkSMS starts up and signs in and I get this notification appear:<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PFO4tCzM4hU/TmhBzgUoyxI/AAAAAAAAACk/l2VJNWYCIF0/s1600/online.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="173" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PFO4tCzM4hU/TmhBzgUoyxI/AAAAAAAAACk/l2VJNWYCIF0/s320/online.png" width="320" /></a></div><br /><br />Then when I pull it off the dock, GTalkSMS signs out and I get this notification:<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Xwq4VMTPyNw/TmhB6BYJfrI/AAAAAAAAACo/Hu2KWVTrADw/s1600/offline.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="173" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Xwq4VMTPyNw/TmhB6BYJfrI/AAAAAAAAACo/Hu2KWVTrADw/s320/offline.png" width="320" /></a></div><br /><br />Note: The notify-send command is available from the <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">libnotify-bin</span> package, which can be installed in Ubuntu with this command:<br /><blockquote><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">sudo apt-get install libnotify-bin</span></blockquote>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
