<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: patch | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/patch/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-10T16:50:52+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git stash, diff and patch]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/git-diff-and-patch.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-21T10:41:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2011/09/git-diff-and-patch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently found myself in a situation where I need to comment out certain lines in my code in order to test a particular set of features.</p>

<p>These commented out lines are only for my local development environment but will be useful in the future if this set of features needs work again.<br/>
In this situation, checking them into Git or making a personal <code>.gitignore</code> file are not really suitable solutions.</p>

<p>I have found two good ways of accomplishing this.</p>

<h2>Git stash</h2>

<p>Starting from a clean checkout, I put my temporary changes in place, then run this command:
<code>
git stash
</code></p>

<p>Then I continue on with my work. I selectively leave these changes out of all my commits using <code>git add -i</code> then once everything is checked in except my temporary changes, I revert these temporary changes with <code>git checkout -- .</code> so I&rsquo;m left with a clean repository.</p>

<p>When I need to work on a related feature again, I can list my stashes with:
<code>
git stash list
</code></p>

<p>Then, apply the most recent stash by running this command:
<code>
git stash apply
</code></p>

<p>If you have more than one stash, you can specify which stash you want to apply on the command line. See <code>git stash --help</code> to see more information.</p>

<h2>Git diff and patch:</h2>

<p><code>diff</code> and <code>patch</code> are very useful tools to be familiar with if you ever deal with text. Git&rsquo;s <code>diff</code> output is much the same, and so the <code>patch</code> tool is still very handy!</p>

<p>Starting from a clean checkout, I put my temporary changes in place, then run this command:
<code>
git diff &amp;gt; ~/patches/temp_workaround.patch
</code></p>

<p>Then I continue on with my work. I selectively leave these changes out of all my commits using <code>git add -i</code> then once everything is checked in except my temporary changes, I revert these temporary changes with <code>git checkout -- .</code> so I&rsquo;m left with a clean repository.</p>

<p>When I need to work on a related feature again, I can apply my patch by running this command from the project root:
<code>
patch -p1 &amp;lt; ~/patches/temp_workaround.patch
</code></p>

<p>Both of these methods will put my temporary work arounds in place again which saves me trying to work out which lines I needed to comment out everytime. Saving the stashes and/or patch files with descriptive names means you can find and re-use these temporary changes quite easily in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
