<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T18:09:03+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting started with Ruby on Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/09/getting-started-with-ruby-on-rails.html"/>
    <updated>2012-09-11T13:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/09/getting-started-with-ruby-on-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
<div>I've been using Ruby on Rails for about a year and half now and I'm really enjoying it!&nbsp;At the time of writing (at least in Melbourne) there is lots of demand for Rubyist's, so it's great time to get involved.</div><div>I have a couple of friends who are interested in making the switch from Java to Ruby so I wrote them an email with some pointers on how to get started and then realized it would make a good blog post :)</div><ul></ul><br /><b>Join the community!</b><br /><br />Ruby and Rails are quite well known for their excellent communities, so the first step is to join your local group. For us in Australia, that group is "<i>Ruby On Rails Oceania</i>" (aka RORO).<br />They have meetups on the <i>last Thursday of every month</i>&nbsp;in Melbourne and a pretty active mailing list:<br /><ul><li><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#%21forum/rails-oceania" target="_blank">Ruby On Rails Oceania Mailing List</a></li><li><a href="http://ruby.org.au/" target="_blank">Ruby.org.au</a></li></ul><br /><b>Ruby and Rails resources:</b><br /><ul><li><a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/">Rails Guides</a>&nbsp;- I use these almost everyday!</li><li><a href="http://apidock.com/">ApiDock</a> - API's for Ruby, Rails and RSpec in one place</li><li><a href="http://railsforzombies.org/">Rails For Zombies</a>&nbsp;- A great beginners tutorial for rails</li><li><a href="http://railscasts.com/">Rails Casts</a>&nbsp;- Regular video podcast all about rails</li><li><a href="http://ruby5.envylabs.com/">Ruby5</a>&nbsp;- Regular 5 minute audio podcast on the latest news</li><li>... a plethora of good books, such as "The RSpec Book", "Design Patterns in Ruby", etc. (alot of which I still need to read)</li></ul><div><br /></div><b>Getting started:</b><br /><br />To get started you'll need to set up your development environment, here's what I use:<br /><ul><li>Vim... of course... although there are lots of alternatives, the most popular ones would probably be:</li><ul><li>RubyMine (IDE) - used alot at work (commercial software)</li><li>Sublime Text 2 (Text editor)</li><li>TextMate (Text editor)</li></ul><li>RVM (Ruby Version Manager)</li><ul><li>Get from here: <a href="https://rvm.io/" target="_blank">https://rvm.io</a></li><li>Follow the instructions to configure your shell to use RVM</li><li>Use RVM to install the latest ruby</li><ul><li>$&gt; rvm install 1.9.3</li></ul><li>A newer alternative to RVM is RBenv</li></ul><li>Once you have ruby installed, you will have the 'gem' command available</li><ul><li>Gems are roughly equivalent to jars in the Java world</li><li>Use gem to install the latest rails</li><ul><li>$&gt; gem install rails</li></ul></ul><li>Once you have rails installed, you will have the 'rails' command available</li><ul><li>Use the rails command to start a new project</li><ul><li>$&gt; rails new todolist</li><li>$&gt; rails server</li><li>browse to <a href="http://localhost:3000/" target="_blank">http://localhost:3000</a></li></ul></ul><li>Now you can read the readme, the rails guides and make a simple app with scaffolding!</li></ul><br /><b>Things to keep in mind for RoR dev:</b><br /><ul><li>Rails is just a framework written in Ruby, so it will help to learn some straight Ruby too.</li><ul><li><a href="http://ruby-lang.org/">ruby-lang.org</a> is a good place to start</li></ul><li>Ruby  on Rails strongly supports DRY principles, don't reinvent the wheel,  theres problably a gem that already does what you want.</li><ul><li>To find gems, good places to look are:</li><ul><li><a href="http://ruby-toolbox.com/" target="_blank">Ruby-Toolbox.com</a></li><li><a href="http://railscasts.com/" target="_blank">RailsCasts.com</a></li><li><a href="http://rubygems.org/" target="_blank">RubyGems.org</a></li><li><a href="http://github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub.com</a></li></ul></ul><li>The majority of Ruby projects are:</li><ul><li>Developed using TDD/BDD, so you'll need to learn the testing frameworks:</li><ul><li>Test::Unit (default with rails)</li><li>RSpec (a popular replacement for Test::Unit)</li><li>Cucumber (BDD)</li></ul><li>Developed on MacOSX - for new comers (like myself) some essentials are:</li><ul><li>brew - a mac package manager (like apt or yum)</li><li>iterm2 - really good terminal emulator</li></ul><li>Deployed on Linux</li><ul><li>Basic Linux foo is really useful</li></ul><li>Version controlled with git</li><ul><li>If you need to learn git, I highly recommend <a href="http://git-scm.com/book">Pro git</a></li></ul></ul></ul><div><br /></div><div>That's a quick overview of what I can recommend to get going based on my own experience, things will obviously change over time, and others may have other opinions, if so feel free to leave comments below.</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
