<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: calendar | StevenOcchipinti.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/categories/calendar/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T22:14:16+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Occhipinti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Calendar - Repeating an event on the last <weekday> of the month]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/05/google-calendar-repeating-event-on-last.html"/>
    <updated>2012-05-23T12:19:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stevenocchipinti.com/2012/05/google-calendar-repeating-event-on-last</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I regularly attend <a href="http://ruby.org.au/">RORO &ndash; The Ruby on Rails Oceania</a> meetups.
They currently occur on the last Thursday of every month and so naturally I put the event in my calendar. I added the usual details and then selected the &ldquo;repeat&rdquo; option and set it to repeat monthly by the day of the week.</p>

<p>This worked well for a while, until one day when I rocked up and it wasn&rsquo;t on.<br/>
A later realised that in that particular month there were 5 Thursdays instead of 4 and my calendar event was actually set to repeat <em>&ldquo;Monthly on the fourth Thursday&rdquo;</em>.<br/>
It turns out that the interface Google provide to set recurring events does not allow you to change this.. or at least not intuitively.</p>

<p>After some searching around I found a few solutions:</p>

<h2>Use English!</h2>

<p>The simplest way is to just write out the event in plain English. For example:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>RORO at Inspire9, Richmond on the last Thursday of every month</p></blockquote></p>

<p>This will create an event called &ldquo;RORO at Inspire9, Richmond&rdquo;, with the location field set to &ldquo;Inspire9, Richmond&rdquo; and the repetition set to <em>&ldquo;Monthly on the last Thursday&rdquo;.</em></p>

<h2>Start repeating from an appropriate month</h2>

<p>Another fairly easy way is to find a month that actually has 5 Thursdays and make the event start from there. This will set the recurrence to repeat <em>&ldquo;Monthly on the last Thursday&rdquo;</em>, instead of <em>&ldquo;Monthly on the fourth Thursday&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Hack the ICS</h2>

<p>This solution is probably the hardest, but because the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ICalendar">iCalendar</a> format does support this, you could write the code manually. To do this you would have to export the calendar to a file, hack it and import it back.<br/>
While it&rsquo;s nice to know this, seems like more effort that just typing what you want in English!</p>

<h2>A better solution</h2>

<p>.. would be if Google provided an additional option in the little &ldquo;repeat&rdquo; popup to allow this!</p>

<p>Or maybe the RORO organiser should maintain there own calendar feed that we could all subscribe to. This would also mean that if a particular meetup was moved or cancelled, all the subscribers calendars would automatically be updated!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
